<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<!-- Link to the XSL Style Sheet -->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./samori-tei.xsl"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>ALIMAMA SAMORI KO-MA: (Histoire l'imam Samori): A critical edition and translation </title>
				<author>Amadou Kouroubari</author>
				<editor xml:id="MD">Maurice Delafosse</editor>
				<principal xml:id="CD">Coleman Donaldson</principal>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p>This is an XML version of one section of Maurice Delafosse's 1901 publication.</p>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>This is a digital XML adaptation of Part III of the following publication: "Delafosse, Maurice. 1901. Essai de manuel pratique de la langue mandé ou mandingue : étude grammaticale du dialecte dyoula : vocabulaire français-dyoula - histoire de
					Samori en mandé : étude comparée des principaux dialectes mandé. Paris: Ernest Leroux. http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k5440988h."</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<!-- ADD langDesc -->
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div xml:lang="man" type="chapter">
				<pb n="147"/>
				<head type="original">Samori a gtyu-tigè, a bo-ñya-ra.</head>
				<head type="interpretation">Samori à ju-tigɛ, à bònyara</head>
				<head type="translation">
					Samori's birth and childhood
				</head>
				<ab type="original">
					<foreign xml:lang="ar">Bismillâhi 'rrahmâni 'rrahimi. Alhamdu lillâhi rabbi 'lâlamina. Salla Allâhu ala sayyidina Mohammadi wa ahlihi wa sallama tasliman</foreign><anchor xml:id="A001" corresp="#N001"/></ab>
			</div>
			<div>
				<ab type="original">
					Ni torho bè Amadu Kurubari, ar ka ni uro Dawakala Gimini ra. Nanzara kyè a Kofidugu sigi a ka ni dari ñi ko-ma fò a ye : alimama
					<foreign xml:lang="ar" rend="italics">Samori Ibnu-Lafia</foreign><anchor xml:id="A002" corresp="#N002"/> ko-ma; n ga a fô a ye :</ab>
				<ab type="interpretation">Nê tɔ́gɔ bɛ́ Amadu Kurubari, àrí kà ne wóro Dawakala Gimina rá. Nànsarakɛ́, à Kofidugu-sigi, à kà nê dári ń yé kúma fɔ́ à yé: Alimami Samori kúma; ń kà à fɔ́ à yé.</ab>
				<ab type="translation" xml:lang="en">
					My name is Amadu Kurubari. They gave birth to me in Dawakala Gimini. This Whiteman, while in Kofidugu, he beseeched me to tell him a tale: the tale of Alimami Samori; I told it to him.
				</ab>

				<note xml:id="N001" target="#A001" n="1" anchored="true" place="bottom" resp="MD">Le début de ce récit est en arabe et veut dire: « Au nom de Dieu le Clément, le Miséricordieux. Louange a Dieu le maître des mondes. Que Dieu bénisse notre seigneur Mohammed et sa famille et leur donne le salut! »</note>
				<note xml:id="N002" target="#A002" n="2" anchored="true" place="bottom" resp="MD">
					Ibnu-Lafia, « fils de Lafla » ; ibnu est un mot arabe.</note>

				<pb n="148"/>
				<ab type="original">
					Samori a urra Sanãkoro ra
					<anchor xml:id="A003" corresp="#N003"/>, dugu mi na ar a kiri Koniã. A fa Mãnde-ñga lo, ar a kiri Lafia Ture ; a bè farha-ndẽ. A na Koniã-ñga muso lo, ar a kiri Masorona Kamara; ar ko muso mi a bè ñi-ma.
				</ab>
				<ab type="interpretation">
					Sǎmòri, à wórora Sanankoro rá, dùgu mîn ná, àrí yé à kíri Koɲan. À fà, Màndenka lò, àrí yé à kíri Lafia Ture; à bɛ́ fàngantan. À ná, Koɲanmuso lò. Àri yé à kíri Masorona Kamara; àri kó mùso mìn, à bɛ́ ɲìman.
				</ab>
				<ab type="translation">
					Samori was born in Sanankoro in a land that they call Konya. His father was a Maninka. They called him Lafia Ture. He was a poor man. His mother, she was Konya. They called her Masorona Kamara. People said this woman, she was good.
				</ab>
				<ab type="original">
					La mi na, kũ-tigi ba a bè ta, ar a kiri Sori Burama, a bè Fode dẽ; a kerè-kè lõ dyugu-kè, Koniã-ñga-ru ar byè sira a ñyã. Sori Burama a ka marfa-tigi-ru tyi, ar ka tarha ar gyõ-u mina. Ar safari-kè-barha-ru ye ar wuro doni ta ar bè tarha ra
					Sanàkoro. Masorona a bè ta ane a kyè ane Samori. Marfa-tigi ar ka marfa tyi, ar ka kyè byè farha; katigi ar ka muso-ru mna, ar ka dẽ-u mna ar ka wuro mna. Samori a borra gyona-gyona, ar ti se ka a mna.
				</ab>
				<ab type="interpretation">
					Lá mìn
					<anchor xml:id="A004" corresp="#N004"/>
					ná, kùntígiba
					<anchor xml:id="A005" corresp="#N005"/>
					, à bɛ́ táa, àrí à kíri Sori Burama, à bɛ Fode dén
					<anchor xml:id="A006" corresp="#N006"/>
					; à kɛ̀rɛ́-kɛ-lɔ́n júgukɛ
					<anchor xml:id="A007" corresp="#N007"/>
					, Koɲankaru, àrí byɛ́
					<anchor xml:id="A008" corresp="#N008"/>
					síran à ɲá. Sori Burama, à kà màrifatígirù cí, àri kà tága àri jònw mìna. Àri safarikɛbagaru
					<anchor xml:id="A009" corresp="#N009"/>
					yé
					<anchor xml:id="A010" corresp="#N010"/>
					àri wòrodoni tà àri bɛ́ tágara Sanankoro. Masorona, à bɛ táa àni à kyɛ̀ àni Samori. Marifatigiw
					<anchor xml:id="A011" corresp="#N011"/>
					, àri kà màrifa cí, àri kà kyɛ̀ byɛ́ fàga; katigi àri kà mùsoru mìna, àri kà dénw mìna, àri wòro mìna. Samori, à bɔ́ra jóona-joona, àri tɛ́ sé kà à mìna.
				</ab>
				<ab type="translation">At the time there was a big chief, they called him Sori Burama. He was the son of "Fode". Because of his knowledge of combat, all the people of Koɲan were afraid of him. Sori Burama dispatched his riflemen. They went to get
					themselves slaves. Some itinerant traders that at the time would transport kola nuts were headed to Sanankoro. Masorona was traveling along with her husband and Samori. The riflemen shot their guns, they killed all the men and they took all the
					women, they took all the children and they took the kola. Samori got away quickly, they couldn't catch him.</ab>
				<ab>
					Ar ka Masorona ferè, ar ka a ye a bè lii-ma, ar ka a ta ar tarha ra Burama fè-so, ar ka a fô a ye : « Muso do ye, ani ka a la, ani na na ka a di i ma, e-ta lo. »
				</ab>
				<ab>
					La mi na Samori bilà-koro tè tugu, a ka gyu-tigè kursi-tigi lo, a bè kà-mbere
					<anchor xml:id="A012" corresp="#N012"/>
					. A ka sye-ko a kwo, a tarha ra Sanàkoro ra, a ka a fô Sanàkoro-nga ye : « Ar ka m va farha, ar ka n na mina, ar ka a ta ka tarha Burama fè-so, a bè a gyô. Aluru ar tarha
					ka sorô, ar Burama dari a n na to. » Sanàkoro morhô-ru ar ka a fô a ye. « E gyô-ne lo? fôndô tè i fè : mune-kato ani tarha ka e ko-ma fô Burama ye? » La mi na Samori kasi ra dyugu-kè.
				</ab>
				<ab>
					Katigi a-lele a tarha ra Sori Burama fwo. La mi na Burama a sigi-ra Mandi-na Wuro-koro ra. Samori, sd dô t'a Te, sàni t'a fè, a ti se ka sd sà, a larha-ma.
				</ab>
				<ab>
					A tarha-ma la kele, ane la kele tugu, so tè va, morhô tè ya, Burama marfa-tigi ar ka kerè-kè wolo, dugu-tigi byè ar ka bori tu ra. A ma fùndô ye ka a domû. A larha-ma la word-mvla, a ma do- mu-ni-kè.
				</ab>
				<ab>
					A dô na Mandi-na. a ka a fô Sori Burama ye : « M va, e ni la, ni e-ta gyô lo. X na, a ka ni uro, a ma di ni a-le e-ta gyô lo, a ma di ni n na a bè gyô; i a to, a tarha a dugu ra tugu. » Sori Burama a
				</ab>

				<note xml:id="N003" target="#A003" n="1" place="bottom" anchored="true" resp="MD">
					Samori naquit sans doute vers 1830 ou 1835. — D'après M. Binger, Samori serait né, non à Sanankoro, mais à Bissandougou.
				</note>
				<note xml:id="N012" target="#A012" n="2" place="bottom" anchored="true" resp="MD">
					Samori pouvait avoir alors de quinze à vingt ans: on était alors vraisemblablement en l'année 1850.
				</note>
				<note xml:id="N004" target="#A004" resp="CD">AS and MD give possiblity that "min" in Kong Jula is a demonstrative (that is, a cognate of "nin" in standard Jula)</note>
				<note xml:id="N005" target="#A005" resp="CD">The word "kùntigi" ('chief') is clear, but the rest of the sentence is hard to interpret. It seems that "kùntigi" refers to Sori Burama and that "-ba" is the augmentative suffix. In that case though, "a
					bè ta" becomes hard to interpret since MD only views "ta" as the 'to take'. Alternatively, MD may have mistranscribed "táa" ('to go')</note>
				<note xml:id="N006" target="#A006" resp="CD">Here it is unclear if it is "Fodeden" ('child of a fode') or "Fode dén" ('child of a man named Fode'). MD lists "Fode" in his lexicon as only being a personal name of a man and doesn't
					mention that it originally comes from a title for learned Quranic scholars who have reached a particular level or erudition which can vary depending on the region.
				</note>
				<note xml:id="N007" target="#A007" resp="CD">Potentially one single possessive noun phrase followed by the adverb "júgukɛ"</note>
				<note xml:id="N008" target="#A008" resp="CD">Seems to be "bɛɛ" ('all') in standard Jula and Bambara, but in that case there seems to be no predicate marker. MD may have therefore switched "bɛ́" to "byɛ́"</note>
				<note xml:id="N009" target="#A009" resp="CD">MD glosses this as
					<foreign xml:lang="fr">commerçant; colporteur</foreign>
					and states that "safari" means 'commerce'. There are no clear cognates in AS, Malidaba or Bamadaba. It could potentially be his misinterpretation of "sànnifeere"</note>
				<note xml:id="N010" target="#N010" resp="CD">Kong Jula's habitual marker "ye" most likely</note>
				<note xml:id="N011" target="#A011" resp="CD">MD doesn't pluralize this noun</note>

				<pb n="149"/>

			</div>

			<!--FORMAT TO BE COPIED FOR NEW PARAGRAPHS ETC <div type="chapter"> <pb/> <head type="original"></head> <head type="interpretation"></head> <head type="translaton"></head> <ab type="original"></ab> <ab type="interpretation"></ab> <ab
			type="translation" xml:lang="en"></ab> </div> <head type="interpretation">-->
			<!--</head>-->
		</body>

	</text>
</TEI>
